Guide to the Elizabeth Cady Stanton Papers, 1792-1981 (bulk 1839-1899)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Elizabeth Cady Stanton Papers
1792-1981
1839-1899
Stanton, Elizabeth Cady, 1815-1902
1.4 cubic feet (7 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
The collection contains material related to Elizabeth Cady Stanton's work for women's suffrage, abolition, temperance, and other social causes. Includes family and professional correspondence, biographical and autobigraphical material, transcripts of her speeches, and photographs. Also includes material by others, such as her daughter, Margaret Stanton Lawrence, about the women's movement and Stanton's life and career.
Biographical Note
Elizabeth Cady Stanton (1815-1902), a leader in the struggle for women's rights, was born on 12 November 1815, in Johnstown, NY, and graduated from Emma Willard's Troy Female Seminary in 1832. Through her close relationship with her cousin Gerrit Smith, a wealthy landowner and reformer, and his daughter, Elizabeth Smith Miller, Stanton became interested in the antislavery and temperance movements, and married the abolitionist Henry Stanton in 1840. As reflected in her letters from 1839-1859, her concerns for the next twenty years appear to have been her children (seven born between 1842 and 1859) and family, but it was during this period that she became one of the leaders in the women's rights movement. She helped to organize the first convention in Seneca Falls, NY in 1848 and formed the friendship with Susan B. Anthony that was to be so important for the future of the feminist movement. At the well-attended convention in Seneca Falls, Stanton proposed a resolution advocating suffrage for women. The resolution was the first public demand by women for the vote and, eloquently defended by Frederick Douglass, was finally adopted.
Elizabeth Cady Stanton's letters, which span the years 1867-1885 and include several to Paulina Wright Davis, another feminist and suffragist, reveal the public person. She became a very popular lecturer on the Lyceum circuit at this time and used her fame and popularity to further the cause of women's rights throughout the United States and abroad. Stanton persuaded Aaron Sargent of California to introduce a federal woman suffrage amendment following the wording of the Fifteenth Amendment. It was reintroduced in every Congress until finally adopted in 1920. In the 1880s, Stanton and Susan B. Anthony prepared the monumental three-volume History of Woman Suffrage, the last volume of which appeared in 1886.
In later years, Stanton, famous and widely honored, devoted more time to writing for newspapers and magazines such as the Westminster Review, Arena, Forum, and North American Review. Still, another controversy involved her. Convinced that the church and its interpretation of the Bible were great obstacles to the progress of women, she demanded that women have an equal place in the church and published The Woman's Bible, a commentary analyzing the Bible's derogatory references to women. These activities are reflected in her letters from 1885-1902.
In 1898, Stanton published her reminiscences, Eighty Years and More, and continued to express her views on religion, divorce, and other subjects. She died at the age of eighty-six. For months afterwards, newspapers and magazines acknowledged Elizabeth Cady Stanton as "a statesman of the woman's rights movement and the mother of woman suffrage."
Scope and Content Note
The collection includes correspondence with Susan B. Anthony, Paulina Wright Davis, Elizabeth Smith Miller, Gerrit Smith, and others relating to family matters, her children, the women's movement, her lectures and travels, publication of her books and articles, women and religion, abolition, temperance, and other social causes, 1839-1902; phrenological report by L.N. Fowler on the character of Stanton, 1853; and clippings, articles, transcripts of her speeches, an autobiographical sketch, and photographs. Other items include correspondence by Margaret Stanton Lawrence and others on the women's movement, other social causes, and Stanton's career, 1792-1927; and manuscripts and typescripts by Margaret Stanton Lawrence about Elizabeth Cady Stanton's life and career.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Names:
Lawrence, Margaret Stanton; Fowler, L.N. (Lorenzo Niles), 1811-1896; Anthony, Susan B. (Susan Brownell), 1820-1906; Davis, Paulina W. (Paulina Wright), 1813-1876; Miller, Elizabeth Smith, 1822-1911; Smith, Gerrit, 1797-1874; Stanton family
Subjects:
Family--New York (State); Women's rights; Women--Suffrage; Slavery--Anti-slavery movements; Women and religion; Temperance; Women--Social conditions; Feminist literature--Women authors; Women travelers; Phrenology; Abolitionists; Feminists; Women authors, American; Women social reformers
Document Types:
Autobiographies; Autographs; Correspondence; Photographs; Printed ephemera; Scrapbooks
VCL Categories:
Family; Religion; Women's History
Encoding Information
Encoded by Elizabeth Clarke, August 2007. Updated by Emma Gronbeck, May 2023.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Harriot Stanton Blatch (VC 1878) and Alma Lutz (VC 1912).
Other Formats
Scrapbooks are also available on microfilm. With the exception of extenuating circumstances, readers will be required to use the microfilm. A part of "Phrenological Character of Mrs. Elizabeth [sic] C. Stanton..." found in Volume 1 of the Scrapbooks was not microfilmed. The reader will find a photocopy of this part in Box 3 of the Stanton Papers.
Series List
- Series I. Correspondence, 1839-1902; (Boxes 1-3)
  This series contains 147 letters (1839-1902) relating to family, children, the women's movement, lectures and travels, publication of Stanton's books, articles, and other topics.
- Series II. Unpublished Manuscripts by Margaret Stanton Lawerence, undated; (Box 4)
  This series contains four unpublished manuscripts by Stanton's daughter about her mother's life and career.
- Series III. Scrapbooks, 1792-1927; (Boxes 5-7)
  This series consists of 3 volumes containing letters written to Elizabeth Cady Stanton from others involved in the women's movement and other causes, as well as clippings of her newspaper articles and letters to the editor, copies of speeches, photographs, and other memorabilia. Volume 1 contains letters from Susan B. Anthony to Stanton and Volume 2 contains a typescript of "Our Young Girls," Stanton's favorite and most popular lecture on the New York Lyceum Bureau circuit.
- Series IV. Miscellaneous, 1839-1981; (Box 3)
  This series consists of additional materials related to Stanton, such as printed articles and ephemera, poetry written by Stanton, biographical and family ephemera, and a photocopy of "Phrenological Character of Mrs. Elizabeth Cady Stanton."
Container List
- Correspondence
  - Susan B. Anthony, 1852 (Folder 1.1.1)
  - Susan B. Anthony, 1855 Jan 3 (Folder 1.1.2)
  - Susan B. Anthony, 1856 Jan (Folder 1.1.3)
  - Susan B. Anthony, 1857 Aug (Folder 1.1.4)
  - Susan B. Anthony, 1859 Apr 4 (Folder 1.1.5)
  - Susan B. Anthony, 1859 Apr 10 (Folder 1.1.6)
  - Susan B. Anthony, 1859 Jul 15 (Folder 1.1.7)
  - Rachel Foster [Avery], [1880s]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.2.1)
  - Rachel Foster [Avery], [1880s]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.2.2)
  - Edward Baines, [1869] Apr 10; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.3)
  - Harriot Stanton Blatch, [1879] Mar 24; (1ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.4)
  - William J. Bok, [1894] Nov 18; (1 ALS w/TS) (Folder 1.5)
  - Mr. Brown, 1872; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.6)
  - [Lloyd] Bryce, [1893 Dec]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.7.1)
  - [Lloyd] Bryce, [1893 Dec 15]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.7.2)
  - C.S. Carter, 1876 Oct 2; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.8)
  - Mrs. Conte, 1885; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.9)
  - Laura Brownell Collier, 1886 Jan 21; (1 ALS w/ env.) (Folder 1.10)
  - Mrs. Darlington, [no year] May 27; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.11)
  - Paulina Wright Davis, [1870 July 9]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.12.1)
  - Paulina Wright Davis, [1872 Apr 1]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.12.2)
  - Paulina Wright Davis, [1874 Oct 18]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.12.3)
  - Mrs. Ellsworth, 1898 Mar 23; (1 LS w/ TS) (Folder 1.13)
  - Mrs. Holloway [?], [1889]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.14)
  - Karr Knortz, 1879 Dec 1; (1 AN w/ TS) (Folder 1.15)
  - Mary Livermore, [1892 Jul 7]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.16.1)
  - Mary Livermore, [1894 May 7]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.16.2)
  - Mrs. William Proctor Mellen, [1890]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.17)
  - Elizabeth Smith Miller, [1839 Jun 4]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.18.1)
  - Elizabeth Smith Miller, [1839 Jul 20]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.18.2)
  - Elizabeth Smith Miller, [1839 Sep 11]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.18.3)
  - Elizabeth Smith Miller, [1841 Mar 17]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.18.4)
  - Elizabeth Smith Miller, [1842 May 28]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.18.5)
  - Elizabeth Smith Miller, [1845 Feb 3]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.18.6)
  - Elizabeth Smith Miller, [1846]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.18.7)
  - Elizabeth Smith Miller, [1847 Feb]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.18.8)
  - Elizabeth Smith Miller, [1847]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.18.9)
  - Elizabeth Smith Miller, [1850 Apr 30]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.18.10)
  - Elizabeth Smith Miller, [1851 Jul 2]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.18.11)
  - Elizabeth Smith Miller, [1852 Oct 22]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.18.12)
  - Elizabeth Smith Miller, [1856 Jan 24]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.18.13)
  - Elizabeth Smith Miller, [1856 Mar]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.18.14)
  - Lucretia Mott, [1872] Apr 1; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.19)
  - Olive Moulton, [1870s]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.20)
  - Charles Mumford, [1871 Apr 29]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.21.1)
  - Charles Mumford, [1870s]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 1.21.2)
  - Elizabeth Pease [Nichol], [1840] Nov 3; (1 ALS w/ TS, env.) (Folder 2.1)
  - Mr. Nordoff, [no year] Apr 15; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 2.2)
  - M.D. Phillips, 1886 Aug 5; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 2.3.1)
  - M.D. Phillips, 1896 Aug 30; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 2.3.2)
  - Mr. Redpath, 1870 Feb 28; (1 ALS w/TS) (Folder 2.4)
  - William Seward, [no year] Sep 19; (1 TS) (Folder 2.5)
  - Mrs. Smith, [no year] Jun 4; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 2.6)
  - Cousin G. [Gerrit Smith], [1874] Dec 16; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 2.7)
  - Margaret [Marguerite Berry Stanton], 1867 Jun 24; (ALS w/ 2 TS) (Folder 2.8.1)
  - Margaret [Marguerite Berry Stanton], 1896 Aug 30; (ALS w/ 2 TS) (Folder 2.8.2)
  - Mr. Strickland, [1886 May]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 2.9)
  - Mr. [Edwin A.] Studwell, 1867 Nov 30; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 2.10)
  - C.P. Sumerby, 1876 Nov 1; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 2.11)
  - Mrs. Thomas, [1898] Feb 19; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 2.12)
  - Mr. Thomas, [1898] Jan 23; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 2.13)
  - Mr. Underhill, [1890]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 2.14)
  - Mrs. Underwood, 1884 Apr 5 - [1890-1898] Jan 23; (8 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 2.15)
  - Mr. Underwood, [1885 Mar 13]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 2.16.1)
  - Mr. Underwood, [1885 Mar 27]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 2.16.2)
  - Mr. Underwood, [1885 Oct 19]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 2.16.3)
  - Mr. Underwood, [1889 Jan 29]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 2.16.4)
  - Mr. Underwood, [1898 Feb 15]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 2.16.5)
  - Mr. Underwood, [1898 Feb 17]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 2.16.6)
  - Mr. Underwood, [1890]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 2.16.7)
  - Mr. Underwood, undated; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 2.16.8)
  - Oswald Villard, 1902 Oct 20; (2 TS w/ env) (Folder 2.17)
  - William Hayes Ward, [1870 Mar 18]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 2.18.1)
  - William Hayes Ward, [1890 Jan 13]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 2.18.2)
  - William Hayes Ward, [1890 Mar 14]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 2.18.3)
  - William Hayes Ward, [1890 Dec 5]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 2.18)
  - Lemuel Washburn, [1893 Mar 25]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 2.19.1)
  - Lemuel Washburn, [1898 Dec 11]; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 2.19.2)
  - Mr. [Thurlow] Weed, [no year] Jan 26; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 2.20)
  - Mrs. White, [1896] Jul 14; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 2.21)
  - B.W. Williams, [1872] Oct 18; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 2.22)
  - Unknown, [1869 Jan 29]; (1 ALS w/TS) (Folder 2.23.1)
  - Unknown, [1870]; (1 ALS w/TS) (Folder 2.23.2)
  - Unknown, [1889 Oct 16]; (1 ALS w/TS) (Folder 2.23.3)
  - Unknown, [1890 Nov 16]; (1 ALS w/TS) (Folder 2.23.4)
  - Unknown, [1895 Jul 28]; (1 ALS w/TS) (Folder 2.23.5)
  - Unknown, [1895 Dec 11]; (1 ALS w/TS) (Folder 2.23.6)
  - Unknown, [1898 Mar 3]; (1 ALS w/TS) (Folder 2.23.7)
  - Unknown, [no year] Aug 27; (1 ALS w/TS) (Folder 2.23.8)
  - Unknown, undated; (1 ALS w/TS) (Folder 2.23.9)
  - Postcard, self – addressed, [1897 Mar]; (1 postcard) (Folder 2.24.1)
  - Postcard, self – addressed, [1897 May]; (1 postcard) (Folder 2.24.2)
  - Postcard, self – addressed, [1897 Feb]; (1 postcard) (Folder 2.24.3)
  - Postcard, self – addressed, [1897 May]; (1 postcard) (Folder 2.24.4)
  - Postcard, self – addressed, [1897 Aug]; (1 postcard) (Folder 2.24.5)
  - Postcard, self – addressed, [1897 Jun]; (1 postcard) (Folder 2.24.6)
  - Postcard, self – addressed, [1897 May]; (1 postcard) (Folder 2.24.7)
  - Postcard, self – addressed, [1897 Mar]; (1 postcard) (Folder 2.24.8)
  - Theodore Tilton, 1897 Mar 27; (1 ALS) (Folder 3.1)
  - Martha C. Wright, 1874 Oct 3; (1 ALS w/ TS) (Folder 3.2)
  - Correspondence to and from Margaret Stanton Lawrence, 1911 Mar 3; (1 ALS, 2 Fragments) (Folder 3.3.1)
  - Correspondence to Margaret Stanton Lawrence, 1923 Jul 2; (1 TS) (Folder 3.3.2)
  - Autograph Notes, 1869 Mar 1 (Folder 3.4.1)
  - Autograph Notes, 1869 Mar 1 (Folder 3.4.2)
  - Autograph Notes, 1871 Feb 18 (Folder 3.4.3)
  - Autograph Notes, 1874 Feb 13 (Folder 3.4.4)
  - Autograph Notes, 1875 Nov 14 (Folder 3.4.5)
  - Autograph Notes, 1885 Dec 1 (Folder 3.4.6)
  - Autograph Notes, 1888 Mar 30 (Folder 3.4.7)
  - Autograph Notes, 1893 Mar (Folder 3.4.8)
  - Autograph Notes, 1893 Oct 11 (Folder 3.4.9)
  - Autograph Notes, 1896 Feb 7 (Folder 3.4.10)
  - Autograph Notes, 1896 Mar 20 (Folder 3.4.11)
  - Autograph Notes, 1896 Aug 1 (Folder 3.4.12)
  - Autograph Notes, 1899 Jul 19 (Folder 3.4.13)
  - Autograph Notes, 1900 (Folder 3.4.14)
  - Autograph Notes, undated (Folder 3.5.1)
  - Autograph Notes, undated (Folder 3.5.2)
  - Autograph Notes, undated (Folder 3.5.3)
  - Autograph Notes, undated (Folder 3.5.4)
  - Autograph Notes, undated (Folder 3.5.5)
  - Autograph Notes, undated (Folder 3.5.6)
  - Autograph Notes, undated (Folder 3.5.7)
- Unpublished Manuscripts by Margaret Stanton Lawerence
  - "Elizabeth Cady Stanton..." pp. 1-43, undated (Folder 4.1)
  - "Elizabeth Cady Stanton..." pp. 44-88, undated (Folder 4.2)
  - "Elizabeth Cady Stanton..." pp. 89-134, undated (Folder 4.3)
  - "Who Was Elizabeth Cady Stanton and Who Started Votes For Women", undated (Folder 4.4)
  - "Who Was Elizabeth Cady Stanton? My Mother," part 1, undated (Folder 4.5)
  - "Who Was Elizabeth Cady Stanton? My Mother," part 2, undated (Folder 4.6)
  - "Who Was Elizabeth Cady Stanton? My Mother," part 3, undated (Folder 4.7)
  - Elizabeth Cady Stanton and the Federal Amendment, undated (Folder 4.8)
- Scrapbooks
  - Volume I, 1792-1870 (Box 5)
  - Volume II, 1881-1899 (Box 6)
  - Volume III, 1892-1921 (Box 7)
- Miscellaneous
  - Inscription of Cook Book from Elizabeth Cady Stanton, 1878 Oct 2; (1 ANS w/ facsimile of inscription, 1 TS) (Folder 3.6)
  - Biographical Sketch by Elizabeth Cady Stanton, 1885 Mar 10; (1 AN w/ TS) (Folder 3.7)
  - Verses by Elizabeth Cady Stanton, [1870 Nov 12]; (1 AN w/ 1 TS) (Folder 3.8)
  - Birthday Poems by Elizabeth Cady Stanton, 1897 Oct 20; (1 AN w/ env) (Folder 3.9.1)
  - Birthday Poems by Elizabeth Cady Stanton, 1852 Oct 20; (1 AN w/ env) (Folder 3.9.2)
  - Toasts by Elizabeth Cady Stanton at Ellen Walter's Dinner Party, undated; (1 AN w/ TS) (Folder 3.10)
  - Robert Livingston Stanton's Toast to Elizabeth Cady Stanton, undated; (1 AN) (Folder 3.11)
  - Bookplate of Theodore Stanton, undated (Folder 3.12)
  - First-day-of-issue envelope honoring Elizabeth Cady Stanton, 1948 Jul 19; (1 env) (Folder 3.13)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material: "The Birth of an Idea" from Lucretia and Elizabeth by Katharine Fisher, undated (Folder 3.14.1)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material: "Tributes to Elizabeth Cady Stanton" from Equal Rights, 1939 Dec (Folder 3.14.2)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material: Lithograph portrait of Elizabeth Cady Stanton, engraved by H. B. Hall, Jr. (from Eminent Women of the Age by James Parton), circa 1869 (Folder 3.14.3)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material: "Elizabeth Cady Stanton" by Helen Waltermire in Hudson River Magazine, 1941 Jan (Folder 3.14.4)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material: "Life Sketch of Elizabeth Cady Stanton" by Nora Stanton Barney, 1948 Jul 19 (Folder 3.14.5)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material: "Stanton, Elizabeth Cady" from The Biographical Cyclopaedia of American Women, Vol. 1, circa 1924 (Folder 3.14.6)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material: "Actor's donation helps preserve historic home" from The Poughkeepsie Journal, 1981 Jun 2 (Folder 3.14.7)
  - Photograph: Portrait of Elizabeth Cady Stanton, 1871 (Folder 3.15.1)
  - Photograph: Portrait of Elizabeth Cady Stanton, undated (Folder 3.15.2)
  - Photograph: Portrait of Elizabeth Cady Stanton with Harriot Stanton Blatch and Nora Stanton Barney, circa 1887 (Folder 3.15.3)
  - Photographs: Portraits of Elizabeth Cady Stanton and her family, 1857-1882 (Folder 3.15.4-6)
  - Photograph: Elizabeth Cady Stanton, undated (Folder 3.15.7)
  - Photograph: Portrait of Judge Daniel Cady, undated (Folder 3.15.8)
  - Photograph: Elizabeth Cady Stanton, undated (Folder 3.15.9)
  - Photograph: Elizabeth Cady Stanton sitting in a chair outside, undated (Folder 3.15.10)
  - "Phrenological Character of Mrs. Elizabeth Cady Stanton", 1853; (Photocopy) (Folder 3.16)